<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Long Winded on T.J. Barbour</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/long-winded/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Long Winded on T.J. Barbour</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Code released under the Apache 2.0 license..</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2015 01:43:44 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/long-winded/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Journey of the T.J.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/TheJourneyOfTJ/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2015 01:43:44 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/TheJourneyOfTJ/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;#Tell me more&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would it be unprofessional to say &amp;ldquo;I HAZ TEH CODEZ!&amp;rdquo; ?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;that&amp;rsquo;s a rhetorical question, and I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly &amp;lsquo;HAZ&amp;rsquo; them anyway&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now here is a story, all about how, my life of coding went up from down:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ignorance-learning:2967bca56255a48f248786b563f388ae&#34;&gt;Ignorance (Learning)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, so I&amp;rsquo;ve grown up around computers, I remember beeping modems and booting to DOS (ok, not quite as impressive as the Commodore 64 generation, but&amp;hellip;).
I was a genuine nerd as a kid, but somehow learning computer programming eluded me.  It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until, after a bafflingly fortunate decision to major in computer engineering, that I finally was enlightened to the powers of these curly-braced enclosed statements&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since my first programming class, I&amp;rsquo;ve been tinkering and learning, and tinkering&amp;hellip; and learning&amp;hellip; you get the picture.  As a family man, I was determined to give my family a good life and got straight on the career path.  Interning while at university and moving onto a full-time role right after graduation in 2006 to the very company I&amp;rsquo;m still working at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Less Ignorance (Working)
Though I had only 1 web application under my belt from college, I was thrust into web development in a unique department where Security was our top priority but we tried to make flexible system designs and hit delivery dates as we coordinated with product teams.  Thankfully they trained us padawans well, involving us in design meetings and accepting our input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a few years I learned the ropes (slippery as some of them are) of ASP.net development and also made some key contributions such as improving some system performance by orders of magnitude all while I learned more about good system design and what approaches worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Not Bliss (Really Learning)
One project in particular really helped me find my niche.  We were a team with little Web Front-End experience (HTML, CSS, JavaScript) so I was yearning for a way for us to stay in ignorance while having more control of the UI on the client side.  Microsoft tempted us (successfully) with Silverlight.  We could write C# code (which we were all familiar with, coding WinForms like nobody&amp;rsquo;s business) that could run directly in the browser.  I clamored for us to use Silverlight in an upcoming project, and we found our &amp;ldquo;crash test dummy&amp;rdquo;, an administrative website configuring a back-end system.  The design was so logical, perfect mappings to our code concepts and database schema, all in the language we loved.  It seemed like the first step on the road to Perfection, but it was FAARRRR from it&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon reflection, that UI looked like the database just barfed on the screen, with no consideration for the real use cases that spanned multiple data entities or performance needs (let alone the burden of end-users installing silverlight) coupled with some holes in the programming model that left us to repeat patterns left and right, and also robbed talented developers of their time to come up with smart &amp;lsquo;solutions&amp;rsquo; to fix said holes, ultimately lead to a horrible product that would go through several re-writes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Bounce Back
I fought the web and the web won.  I thought I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to really learn about this &amp;lsquo;web&amp;rsquo; thing (a second class citizen to any &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; programmer [note the sarcasm quotes.)  Thankfully, &lt;strong&gt;jQuery&lt;/strong&gt; was the new hawtness and I finally took the leap to start stepping down from my server-side ivory tower and see this land of Web Front-End.  There I found great power, precise control of every element and its behavior, with only some (albeit annoying) browser quirks to deal with!  I was reinvigorated, and suddenly I had some unique skills on my team.  I transitioned us over to ASP.net MVC which lead developers naturally into a &lt;a href=&#34;http://codeblog.jonskeet.uk/2010/09/02/presentation-preparation/&#34;&gt;pit of success&lt;/a&gt; and we began to really harness the Web (well, at least compared to what we used to do&amp;hellip;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Up to 11
I now took my inner desires for symmetry and order that I would express as a child with pattern blocks and could apply it beyond the code scope, but at a higher level.  I noticed that there were many repeated patterns and styles and interfaces and behaviors and so much repeated HTML, that it drove me to take action.  I gained experience of good UIs and what UX was through trial and error, exposure at conferences and more learning&amp;hellip; and tinkering&amp;hellip; and learning&amp;hellip; and tinkering&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward, and now we have (thanks to lots of help and the great tools in the .net system today)  re-usable NuGet packages that greatly simplify web development and share styles across the whole department.  All of this simplifies web development and enables &amp;ldquo;web-ignorant&amp;rdquo; programmers to get a lot done without having to know too much front-end details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Today
I am so glad that I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to gain this experience, its truly a blessing.  Now I want to take my talents to south beach&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software development is my passion.  It is a balance of speed, quality, innovation, standards, perfection, imperfection, machines, people, business and fun.  Always eager to learn and teach in an effort to improve our industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time I&amp;rsquo;m looking for a &lt;strong&gt;remote&lt;/strong&gt; full time position.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>